welcome back to APUSH in under 3 minutes
no time for intros let's get into it
topic 4.2 is about the age of
Jefferson's term in office and really
what just happened so Thomas Jefferson a
DieHard Democratic Republican takes
office after the Federalist rule of
Adams continuing into this period we
have these two parties debating over
relations with the French and the
British and powers of the federal
government all things covered in my
topic 3.10 video but we start seeing
debates over something new around this
period known as tariffs which is a tax
on imported goods meaning Goods coming
into America this tax is paid by
American companies which typically raise
their prices to accommodate for the tax
understand that in a world where the
south is typically known as a rural
agrarian expanse known for farming and
the north is known for their Industries
and manufacturers the South would be
negatively affected by these tariffs as
they need to import lots of goods
because of the lack of Industries they
have the north would benefit from this
tax As Americans would start only buying
American manufactured goods the
Democratic Republicans hated the idea of
tariffs aligning themselves with the
South the Federalists liked the ideas of
tariffs aligning themselves with a
northern view during Jefferson's
presidency he enacted the trade Embargo
of 1807 which made it so America would
stop importing Britain's Goods this
would end up backfiring and hurting the
American economy but possibly the most
famous part of Jefferson's presidency
was the case Marbury V Madison which was
a Supreme Court case that established
the concept of judicial review which
allowed the Supreme Court to review and
invalidate actions taken by the other
branches of government if they are
deemed unconstitutional and another
popular thing is even more Westward
Expansion the US wanted the land of New
Orleans and negotiated with France to
get it France offered the entire
Louisiana territory as they were facing
Financial issues because of Napoleon and
the US bought it for $15 million now
with all this territory the US wanted to
map it so they sent Lewis and Clark on
an expedition with the Native American
guide of saaka to help them they went
all the way from St Louis to the Pacific
and mapped out the western territories
and realized truly how big it was on the
screen now are some AP style questions
for this topic pause
now I'll put the answers on the screen
now I will see you in the next one